Finding Aid for Elizabeth Ann Allen papers
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Elizabeth Ann Allen papers1918-2014 1930-2013
Allen, Elizabeth A.
3.08 GB online
1 linear foot
2015036 Aa 2
Associate Professor in the University of Michigan School of Nursing and Head Nurse of the Surgical Intensive Care Unit at the 71st Evacuation Hospital in Pleiku during the Vietnam War. Major Elizabeth Allen advocated for veterans, particularly women and African Americans, and campaigned for greater awareness of veterans' issues, including Post-Traumatic Stress Disorder and its effect on military families. Materials include personal and family military, financial, and medical records, as well as photographs, digital video content, correspondence, personal writings, and newspaper clippings.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Donated by Elizabeth Ann Allen (donor no. 11231 ) in February, 2015.
Periodic additions to the records expected.
The collection is open without restriction with the exception of digital video content which can be viewed in the Bentley Library only.
Elizabeth Ann Allen was born in Huntington, West Virginia in 1940. Her mother died when she was a young child and she and her four siblings were raised by her grandmother. During her high school years, public schools in the south were desegregated and Allen was encouraged by her teachers to enroll in the historically white high school. She excelled in school, particularly in the areas of math and science, but was one of the few African Americans in her school and faced discrimination from her teachers and classmates daily. She was able to succeed in spite of this adversity and went on to pursue a college education.
She received a Bachelor of Science and a Master of Science in Nursing, in 1965 and 1966 respectively, from the Ohio State University. In 1967, inspired by her brother's service, she voluntarily joined the United States Army Nurse Corps at the rank of Captain and requested assignment on the front lines of the Vietnam War. She was one of fewer than 100 African American nurses deployed. She reported to the 12th Evacuation Hospital at Cu Chi and remained there for about six months before being assigned as Head Nurse of the Surgical Intensive Care Unit at the 71st Evacuation Hospital in Pleiku. During this time, in 1968, Pleiku was targeted in the first round of surprise attacks known as the Tet Offensive.
Upon her return to the United States, Allen trained Army medics to act as psychiatric practitioners in the field at Valley Forge General Hospital in Pennsylvania. In 1969, she was appointed, State Director for Psychiatric Nursing for the South Carolina Department of Mental Health and later went on to become Assistant Professor of Nursing at the University of South Carolina where she received her PhD in 1973. She joined the faculty of the School of Nursing at the University of Michigan in 1976. In addition to her duties as a faculty member, she acted as Director of the Center for Continuing Education for Nurses, a position she held until 1982. In 1985, she served as Acting Director of Minority Affairs at the University. Throughout her professional career, she advocated for veterans, and spoke on veterans' issues, such as Post-Traumatic Stress Disorder and the treatment of women and African Americans in the military. She was appointed by Governor James Blanchard, in 1987, to the Agent Orange Commission and was twice elected as chair. She continued to serve as a Major in the Active Army Nurse Corps Reserve until 1988. As a professor, she worked to create awareness among her students of the ways in which poverty, race, and social justice can have an impact on the field of nursing. Allen retired from her position as Associate Professor in 2007 and was named Associate Professor Emerita of Nursing by the University Regents that same year.
The collection has been arranged into two series, Personal and Professional.
The papers of Major Elizabeth Allen document her service in the United States military as well as that of three generations of her family. The papers highlight her personal experiences with the military, Post-traumatic Stress Disorder, and Agent Orange; however they also include materials about her teaching and professional service. Materials include correspondence, family financial records, newspaper clippings, unpublished written works, photographs, biographical materials, newsletters and collected magazines, and academic articles.
Subjects:
African American nurses.; African American women--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Agent Orange.; Allen, Elizabeth A.; Desegregation in education.; Huntington (W. Va.); Pleiku (Vietnam); Post-traumatic stress disorder.; Tet Offensive, 1968.; United States. Army Nurse Corps.; University of Michigan. School of Nursing--Faculty.; Vietnam Veterans of America.; Vietnam War, 1961-1975.; Vietnam War, 1961-1975--African Americans.; Vietnam War, 1961-1975--Medical care.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
African Americans.
Genre Terms:
Digital moving formats.; Photographs.
- Personal
  The Personal series (ca. 1910-2011, 0.7 linear feet) includes a wide variety of materials. Family financial and military records, as well as photographs and correspondence provide insight into the experiences and struggles faced by generations of Allen's family as African Americans living in the southern United States striving toward the middle class. This series also includes Allen's personal writings and other records which document her experience with PTSD. Digital video content illustrating Allen's experience as an Army nurse in Vietnam and the effects of her exposure to Agent Orange are also present in this series. Videos are accessible online in the Bentley Library only by following the links in this finding aid.
  - Biographical Materials, circa 1991-2011
    - Curriculum Vitae and Autobiography, circa 1991 (Box 1)
    - Vietnam documentary series, Episode 3 draft, History Channel, 2011, .ZIP and .MP4 files)
    - Vietnam Veterans of America and Agent Orange Education Campaign video, circa 2011, .ZIP and .MP4 files
  - Correspondence, 1990-2011 (Box 1)
  - Department of Veteran Affairs, 2007, 2009 (Box 1)
  - Family Correspondence, 1936-1977 (Box 1)
  - Family Military Records, 1918-1952 (Box 1)
  - Family Records, 1910s-1990s and undated, 7 folders (Box 1)
  - Photographs, circa 1910-2000s (Box 1)
  - Poems, Lyrics, and Therapy Materials, circa 1990s (Box 1)
  - Writings, 1990s-2000s (Box 1)
- Professional
  The Professional series (1985-2014, 0.3 linear feet) includes newspaper clippings, newsletters, and magazines, many of which feature Allen and her work. The series also includes scholarly articles collected by Allen on topics of interest, including African Americans and women in the military and nursing. Materials relating to her work on the Agent Orange Commission can be found in this series as well as other resources on the topic. Additionally, ephemera from various conferences and presentations as well as professional awards can be found here.
  - Articles, 1989-1994 (Box 1)
  - Newsletters and Magazines, 1988-2013 (Box 1)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1985-2012 (Box 1)
  - Presentations and Awards, 1988-2014 (Box 1)
  - Professional Service, 1990-2006 (Box 1)
Related Materials
Materials relating to School of Nursing faculty, Vietnam veterans, and Elizabeth Allen may be found in the Bernadine Cimprich papers and Vietnam Veterans of America, Chapter 9 (Detroit, Mich.) records at the Bentley Historical Library. Researchers may also wish to consult the Elizabeth A. Allen Collection, which is part of the Veterans History Project at the American Folklife Center (http://lcweb2.loc.gov/diglib/vhp/bib/loc.natlib.afc2001001.55266).